Metcalf Hall Protest Posters and Resident Life Records UA249
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Metcalf Hall Protest Posters and Resident Life Records
circa 1969 -- 1976
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
UA249
3 Linear Feet
54 Digital Object(s)
This collection contains protest posters and resident life records from Metcalf Hall.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred by Vikram Krishnamakari and Chloe Amouyal, residents of Metcalf Hall, 2018, accession UA-2018-054.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in two series: Protest posters, and Resident Life records.
Metcalf Hall
Metcalf Hall was constructed in 1893 to serve as a dormitory for women students. It was named for Albert Metcalf, member of the Board of Trustees, who donated funds to construct the building. It was designed by J. Philip Rinn.
The building included a dining hall for women, and was supervised by a house matron. Residents were allowed to receive guests only in common area, and were required to be in their rooms by 10:00 p.m. nightly. The men students quickly dubbed the new residence the "Bird Cage" in honor of its residents.
In 1937 an addition to the west side of the building was made to provide additional housing for women, and nearly doubled the size of the original building.
Currently the building is home to the Metcalf Living and Learning Community, which is supervised by a scholar-in-residence who works with undergraduate students interested in current affairs in politics, education, and ethics and provides opportunities for students to engage Tufts' faculty and each other in a more informal atmosphere.
Student Protests at Tufts, 1960s-1970s
Tufts has a long history of student activism stemming from its founding, but one of the most acute periods of activism ran from 1967 to 1972. Opposition to the Vietnam War and was the biggest catalyst for student protest, but students also protested U.S. involvement in apartheid South Africa, for increased representation of and support for African-Americans on campus, and for greater student involvement in the Tufts administration. Opposition to the Vietnam War also prompted student protests against military recruitment and against the presence of the ROTC on campus.
In the fall of 1969, students organized a one-day boycott of classes in opposition to the Vietnam War. There were six major confrontations between the school and student protesters during the 1970-71 academic year. At the Fletcher School, the office of Dean Gullion was firebombed in March 1971 in an apparent act of opposition to his open support for the war and the School's close ties to the military, which had both been a frequent source of criticism from Tufts activists.
Student activism began to decline after the 1971-72 academic year, as the U.S.'s involvement in the Vietnam War drew to a close. Student activism on other issues has continued up to the present.
Custodial History
These materials were discovered in a storage closet at Metcalf Hall by First Year Advisor Vikram Krishnamakari and resident Chloe Amouyal, who then contacted DCA. They were retrieved by Collections Management Archivist Adrienne Pruitt, Archives and Research Assistant Rose Koven, and Public Services and Outreach Archivist Pam Hopkins in April 2018.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains protest posters addressing a variety of topics such as the Vietnam War, nuclear weapons, capitalism, and workers' rights; three checkout binders for residence halls at Tufts University; and a silkscreen for an original student musical that was found with the posters.
Student life; Wren Hall; Tilton Hall; Lewis Hall; Protest movements; Vietnamese Conflict, 1961-1975; Nuclear weapons; Capitalism; Student activism
- Protest posters, circa 1969 -- 1976; UA249.001; 54 Folder(s); .2 Linear Feet; 54 Digital Object(s)
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged alphabetically by poster title, followed by the silkscreen.
  Conditions Governing Access
  This series is open for research.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains protest posters addressing a variety of topics such as the Vietnam War, nuclear weapons, capitalism, and workers' rights. It includes several posters related to Kent State which likely date from spring and summer 1970. It also contains an undated silkscreen advertising an original musical, "Hasty Prophets," found with the protest posters in Metcalf Hall.
  - All free peoples university, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.001.00001; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 1, Box 1)
    Open for research.
    Printed in a variety of colors: "All Free Peoples / University / Power to the People," with a figure of a person in the background.
  - Amerika, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.001.00002; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 2, Box 1)
    Image of a crowd surrounding a dead man. There is a cartoon of a pig in the corner.
  - Au grand jour, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.001.00003; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 3, Box 1)
    Quote by Rene Crevel, text in red.
  - Be realistic…demand the impossible, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.001.00004; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 4, Box 1)
    Text in yellow.
  - Black panther, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.001.00005; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 5, Box 1)
    Image of a black panther wrapped in barbed wire.
  - Boston Herald traveler, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.001.00006; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 6, Box 1)
    Reprint of the front page of the "Boston Herald." The main story is about the Kent State shootings.
  - Cambodia too?, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.001.00007; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 7, Box 1)
    Depicts a man in striped pajamas, a scene from Charlie Chaplin's 1917 film, "The Adventurer." Below the image is the following text: "Cambodia too?"
  - Community involvement weekend, 1970; UA249.001.001.00008; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 8, Box 1)
    Poster for events on May 15-17, 1970 at Tufts.
  - Contemplating more bomb tests, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.001.00009; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 9, Box 1)
    Quote by Eve Merriam.
  - Don't throw rocks, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.001.00010; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 10, Box 1)
    Text in red.
  - Ex president Nixon, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.001.00011; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 11, Box 1)
    Reprint of an interview with former President Richard Nixon in which he explained why he would not be running for another term. The Vietnam War is featured prominently in the article.
  - H.Q.: The White House, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.001.00012; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 12, Box 1)
    Small blue picture of what appears to be a hybrid of a military tank and the United States Capitol building.
  - Hear no evil, see no evil, speak no evil, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.001.00013; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 13, Box 1)
    Red monkeys covering themselves with the American flag.
  - Here have another one, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.001.00014; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 14, Box 1)
    Political cartoon of President Richard Nixon offering a second cigar with the word "Cambodia" written on it to a man. The man's first cigar--entitled "Vietnam"--has just exploded.
  - Huelga, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.001.00015; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 15, Box 1)
    The word "Strike" is written in Spanish and appears below a red power fist.
  - I saw it, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.001.00016; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 16, Box 1)
    Image of two elderly people.
  - Impeach Nixon now, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.001.00017; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 17, Box 1)
    Cover of "Time" magazine of President Richard Nixon.
  - In loyalty to their kind, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.001.00018; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 18, Box 1)
    Quote written in black with a red lightning bolt in the background.
  - It takes $400 per year, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.001.00019; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 19, Box 1)
    Political cartoon of President Richard Nixon riding a tank. Below the cartoon is a brief statement about the cost of the Vietnam War.
  - Liberty strike, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.001.00020; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 20, Box 1)
    A red Statue of Liberty with a raised fist. Underneath the statue is the word "Strike".
  - Love, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.001.00021; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 21, Box 1)
    The word "Love", where the middle two letters have been replaced with a fist and a peace sign. Text written in red.
  - Man in pain, 1970; UA249.001.001.00022; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 22, Box 1)
    Black and red image of two men, one of whom appears to be in pain. Text in the bottom right-hand corner of the image reads: "May 70 A. Smals".
  - Men, 1970; UA249.001.001.00023; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 23, Box 1)
    Multicolored image of men wearing masks and playing the drums. Text in the bottom right-hand corner of the image reads: "May 70 A. Smals".
  - More housing, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.001.00024; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 24, Box 1)
    Depicts a raised fist emerging out of urban homes and buildings. The text reads: "More / Housing / ? / Tax / the / Slumlords". The bottom right hand corner of the poster reads "ABCTU".
  - Mother's day, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.001.00025; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 25, Box 1)
    Purple picture of a militant woman holding a gun and a baby. Below the image is the following text: "Bring our sons home now."
  - Never think that war…, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.001.00026; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 26, Box 1)
    Quote by Ernest Hemingway above a picture of a cemetery.
  - Nixon's the 1, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.001.00027; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 27, Box 1)
    An armed and armored skeleton that is standing in front of the Earth and is flanked by gargoyles. The skeleton's shield is decorated with a swastika.
  - On your knees, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.001.00028; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 28, Box 1)
    Red and white image of three men--two of whom are wearing military clothing and one of whom is wearing a mortarboard--forming a line and kissing each other's bottom. The first in line is kissing money offered by an outstretched hand.
  - Pile the bodies high…, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.001.00029; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 29, Box 1)
    Pictures of two victims of the Kent State Shootings--Allison Krause and Sandra Lee Scheuer--above Carl Sandburg's poem, "Grass". Printed in red.
  - Power fist, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.001.00030; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 30, Box 1)
    A red raised fist.
  - Property or theft?, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.001.00031; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 31, Box 1)
    Picture of a couple holding an American flag and standing in front of a car.
  - Quotation to ponder, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.001.00032; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 32, Box 1)
    A row of tanks and soldiers in riot gear; above them is Uncle Sam, making two V symbol gestures. To the right of the tanks, soldiers, and Uncle Sam, is a quote by Adolf Hitler about strikes, danger, and law and order.
  - Rally at Harvard, 1971; UA249.001.001.00033; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 33, Box 1)
    Advertises a strike at Harvard Stadium on May 30, in protest of the Vietnam War.
  - Sick of the war, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.001.00034; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 34, Box 1)
    Red lettering and picture of a dead man laying on the ground in a pool of blood.
  - Silenced?, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.001.00035; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 35, Box 1)
    Picture of United States Representative H. James Shea Jr.
  - Skeleton, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.002.00001; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 1, Box 2)
    Skeleton wearing a service ribbon and saluting.
  - Stars and strikes?, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.002.00002; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 2, Box 2)
    A red raised fist in front of a star-less and stripe-less United States flag. The corner of the flag references Kent State University and text in the middle of the flag reads: "Stars and Strikes?".
  - Stop the gears, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.002.00003; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 3, Box 2)
    Image of a factory producing missiles.
  - Strange fruit is hard to swallow, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.002.00004; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 4, Box 2)
    Depicts the lynching of Abram Smith and Thomas Shipp.
  - Strike, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.002.00005; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 5, Box 2)
  - Support the strike, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.002.00006; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 6, Box 2)
    The words "Support / The / Strike" appear above a red raised fist.
  - Teachers..join our strike for peace, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.002.00007; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 7, Box 2)
    Depicts a teacher's swivel chair.
  - The strike is for everyone, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.002.00008; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 8, Box 2)
    Depicts a hand holding an olive branch. Text on the sleeve of the hand reads "The strike / Is For / Everyone," and text adjacent to the hand reads "Join / The / Strike / For / Peace".
  - There is some shit we will not eat strike, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.002.00009; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 9, Box 2)
    Taking the format of a newspaper, this item describes strikes against the Vietnam War from around the country.
  - Things don't necessarily go better with coke.., circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.002.00010; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 10, Box 2)
    The poster has two statements: "Things Don't Necessarily / Go Better with Coke.." and "Don't drink Coke / Support the National Economic Boycott".
  - This war destroys families, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.002.00011; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 11, Box 2)
    The poster depicts hooded figures. Below the figures is the following text: "This War / Destroys / Families." Some of the posters have text written in Spanish.
    - Esta guerra destruye a las familias, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.002.00011.00001; 1 Digital Object(s); 390 Megabytes
      The poster depicts hooded figures. Below the figures is the following text: "This War / Destroys / Families." Some of the posters have text written in Spanish. This is a scan of one of nine duplicate posters in the folder.
    - This war destroys families, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.002.00011.00002; 1 Digital Object(s); 383 Megabytes
  - Unite now, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.002.00012; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 12, Box 2)
    Depicts an image from the Kent State shootings.
  - War for us has been a sport, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.002.00013; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 13, Box 2)
    Two blue and white images of a dead child. Behind the child are bombers in flight.
  - We demand, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.002.00014; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 14, Box 2)
    Depicts a raised fist emerging out of urban homes and buildings. The text reads "We / Demand / Maintenance / No Eviction / No / Luxury Apts". The bottom right hand corner of the poster reads "ABCTU".
  - When dissent turns to violence it invites tragedy, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.002.00015; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 15, Box 2)
    Depicts images of President Richard Nixon, the four victims of the Kent State Shootings--Allison Krause, Jeffrey Glen Miller, Sandra Lee Scheuer, and William Knox Schroeder--and several quotes.
  - Withdrawal from Vietnam, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.002.00016; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 16, Box 2)
    A ballot with one question: "Do you favor the immediate withdrawal of United States troops from Vietnam?"
  - Women's solidarity strike, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.002.00017; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 17, Box 2)
    A female/Venus symbol that has been combined with a raised fist.
  - World war 3 is unique, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.002.00018; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 18, Box 2)
    The poster's text reads: "World War III is unique because it will never be mentioned in history books".
  - Write to Congress it helps, circa 1969 -- 1974; UA249.001.002.00019; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1-2, 23, Folder 19, Box 2)
    Image of a dove holding an olive branch. The poster reads: "Write to Congress / It Helps".
  - "Hasty Prophets" silk screen, circa 1969 -- 1976; UA249.001.002.00020; .2 Linear Feet (Box 1-2, 23, Box 2)
    Undated silk screen advertising an original musical, "Hasty Prophets."
- Resident Life records, 1976; UA249.002; 3 Folder(s)
  This series is arranged in received order.
  This series contains checkout binders for three residence halls at Tufts University.
  - Tilton checkout binder, 1976; UA249.002.003.00001; 1 Folder(s) (Box 3)
  - Wren checkout binder, 1976; UA249.002.003.00002; 1 Folder(s) (Box 3)
  - Lewis checkout binder, 1976; UA249.002.003.00003; 1 Folder(s) (Box 3)